<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-07-14T00:29:30-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Joey Rudoler</title><subtitle>Home of a curious data scientist / physicist / musician / literary fanboy</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Modernism is really a bad attempt at the Random Surfing Model</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/07/13/modernism-as-stochasticity.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Modernism is really a bad attempt at the Random Surfing Model" /><published>2021-07-13T23:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-07-13T23:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/07/13/modernism-as-stochasticity</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/07/13/modernism-as-stochasticity.html">&lt;p&gt;Throughout my high school and college years, I was constantly baffled by the prominence of an interdisciplinary artistic movement known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Modernism&quot;&gt;Modernism&lt;/a&gt;. As far as I could tell, the only thing about Modern Art that was consistent was that it was confusing and aesthetically unappealing. Think I’m being harsh? Listen to some of John Cage’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=N0-y8oNDLgU&quot;&gt;prepared piano&lt;/a&gt; and tell me I’m wrong. Anyways, this point will be aimed at trying to talk through my understanding of Modernism, how it’s justified, and why I think it’s still kind of dumb. Disclaimer that my summaries of historical and artistic movements are based 20% off real coursework and 80% off of Wikipedia. 
Modernism as a movement in art is really tied to a deeper philosophy that arose in the late 19th and early 20th centuries which advocated for a departure from the artistic and societal norms which had dominated Western Culture until that point. Following the Dark Ages, art and culture flourished during the Renaissance, and as Renaissance humanism sparked the European Enlightenment people truly began to believe that human ingenuity was powerful enough to effectively perfect ourselves in the domains of science, philosophy, and art. 
The profits of the Industrial Revolution fueled the confidence of artists and scientists alike. The idea of the artistic “genius” who could create art from the depths of his own imagination and emotions was essential to the artistic movement of Romanticism, and on the other side of the spectrum artistic Realists did everything they could to reproduce our world as precisely and as truthfully as possible. While these approaches were aesthetically quite different, they both emphasized tremendous technical expertise. The Enlightenment corresponded to a period of tremendous muscial progress as well, which also saw the rise of veritable “genius” composers like Mozart and Beethoven. Likewise, the speed of scientific progress had reached such a fever pitch that overconfidence was pervasive in the 18th and 19th centuries, and in some cases patently absurd. In 1878 a physicist named &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philipp_von_Jolly&quot;&gt;Philipp von Jolly&lt;/a&gt; (awesome name, by the way) tried to dissuade a young student at the University of Munich by the name of Max Planck from entering the field, claiming that in physics “almost everything is already discovered, and all that remains is to fill a few unimportant holes.” Luckily Planck did not heed his professor’s advice, as his work pioneered quantum theory and earned him the Nobel Prize as he joined Einstein, Schrödinger, and others in completely revolutionizing how we understand matter and the universe.
Understandably, this belief that humans have “figured it out” rubbed some people the wrong way. What if we’re getting it wrong? What if we’re missing something like jazz or, oh I don’t know, relativity theory? As someone who likes math and has a strong interest in machine learning, all this certainty and confidence in humans as “optimizers” of some cultural and scientific cost function still seems crazy. It’s like using a batch gradient descent algorithm with a really small step size - using &lt;em&gt;everyone’s&lt;/em&gt; input and weighting each one very little. This makes culture susceptible to groupthink - whatever is popular and appeals to the masses will continue to be chosen as “optimal”. Modernists try to introduce the possibility for change, and to seek new and fruitful artistic modes, by radically deviating from the norm. This is closer to stochastic gradient descent with a large step size - we add some randomness to the mix.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html">Throughout my high school and college years, I was constantly baffled by the prominence of an interdisciplinary artistic movement known as Modernism. As far as I could tell, the only thing about Modern Art that was consistent was that it was confusing and aesthetically unappealing. Think I’m being harsh? Listen to some of John Cage’s prepared piano and tell me I’m wrong. Anyways, this point will be aimed at trying to talk through my understanding of Modernism, how it’s justified, and why I think it’s still kind of dumb. Disclaimer that my summaries of historical and artistic movements are based 20% off real coursework and 80% off of Wikipedia. Modernism as a movement in art is really tied to a deeper philosophy that arose in the late 19th and early 20th centuries which advocated for a departure from the artistic and societal norms which had dominated Western Culture until that point. Following the Dark Ages, art and culture flourished during the Renaissance, and as Renaissance humanism sparked the European Enlightenment people truly began to believe that human ingenuity was powerful enough to effectively perfect ourselves in the domains of science, philosophy, and art. The profits of the Industrial Revolution fueled the confidence of artists and scientists alike. The idea of the artistic “genius” who could create art from the depths of his own imagination and emotions was essential to the artistic movement of Romanticism, and on the other side of the spectrum artistic Realists did everything they could to reproduce our world as precisely and as truthfully as possible. While these approaches were aesthetically quite different, they both emphasized tremendous technical expertise. The Enlightenment corresponded to a period of tremendous muscial progress as well, which also saw the rise of veritable “genius” composers like Mozart and Beethoven. Likewise, the speed of scientific progress had reached such a fever pitch that overconfidence was pervasive in the 18th and 19th centuries, and in some cases patently absurd. In 1878 a physicist named Philipp von Jolly (awesome name, by the way) tried to dissuade a young student at the University of Munich by the name of Max Planck from entering the field, claiming that in physics “almost everything is already discovered, and all that remains is to fill a few unimportant holes.” Luckily Planck did not heed his professor’s advice, as his work pioneered quantum theory and earned him the Nobel Prize as he joined Einstein, Schrödinger, and others in completely revolutionizing how we understand matter and the universe. Understandably, this belief that humans have “figured it out” rubbed some people the wrong way. What if we’re getting it wrong? What if we’re missing something like jazz or, oh I don’t know, relativity theory? As someone who likes math and has a strong interest in machine learning, all this certainty and confidence in humans as “optimizers” of some cultural and scientific cost function still seems crazy. It’s like using a batch gradient descent algorithm with a really small step size - using everyone’s input and weighting each one very little. This makes culture susceptible to groupthink - whatever is popular and appeals to the masses will continue to be chosen as “optimal”. Modernists try to introduce the possibility for change, and to seek new and fruitful artistic modes, by radically deviating from the norm. This is closer to stochastic gradient descent with a large step size - we add some randomness to the mix.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">First post</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/03/14/first-post.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="First post" /><published>2021-03-14T23:57:13-04:00</published><updated>2021-03-14T23:57:13-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/03/14/first-post</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/03/14/first-post.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve never been much of a blogger, but I guess there’s no time like the present. I have a lot of ideas, so maybe I’ll put them here instead of talking my friends’ ears off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m interested in posting about some of the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Life vignettes that feel poignant and/or educational. I find that writing or talking about important experiences helps me to concretize and digest them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sports! I could talk about Joel Embiid for days on end. #EMVPiid&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Statistics, and statistical decision-making&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Music - I think I have good taste, at least this will help me track what I’ve been listening to.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Books - I’m a painfully slow reader, but I have a soft spot for quality literature. I particularly like modern American Fiction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html">I’ve never been much of a blogger, but I guess there’s no time like the present. I have a lot of ideas, so maybe I’ll put them here instead of talking my friends’ ears off.</summary></entry></feed>